Guide to the San Francisco Planning and Urban Renewal records, [ca.1911-1969]
San Francisco Planning and Urban Renewal records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
San Francisco Planning and Urban Renewal records, [ca.1911-1969]
3199
San Francisco Planning and Urban Renewal Association.
4 cubic ft.
Organizational records, reports, photographs, and printed materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes records related to housing planning and redevelopment; recreation; land use; organizational materials; social policy; and transportation.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The San Francisco Housing Association became the San Francisco Planning and Housing Association, and then the San Francisco Planning and Urban Renewal Association (SPUR). It is now the San Francisco Planning and Urban Research Association.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes records related to housing planning and redevelopment; recreation; land use; organizational materials; social policy; and transportation. Includes paper of Don Emmons as president; reports on housing by Catherine Bauer Wurster; and records of the Pacific Southwest Council of the National Association of Housing and Redevelopment Officials.
SUBJECTS
Names:
San Francisco Planning and Urban Renewal Association.; Emmons, Don; Emmons, Don.; Wurster, Catherine Bauer; Wurster, Catherine Bauer.; National Association of Housing and Redevelopment Officials. Pacific Southwest Council.; San Francisco Housing Association.; San Francisco Planning and Housing Association.
Subjects:
Housing.; Urban renewal.; Land use.; Transportation.; City planning --California --San Francisco.; City planning; Housing; Land use; Transportation; Urban renewal
Places:
San Francisco (Calif.); California --San Francisco
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence, Memos, and News Clippings regarding Public Housing, 1949-1950, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Some dealing with minority occupancy and redevelopment
- Copies of News clippings on Slums and Slum Clearance, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence and other materials related to Congressional and State Assembly Bills dealing with Public Housing and Slum Clearance, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Booklets on Building Standards, 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Booklets on Building Standards; "Opening Statement for the Conference on "Neighborhoods for Family Living" by Oskar Stonorov, 1939, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Real Property Surveys, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Correspondence, Property Surveys and Suggestions for Report in San Francisco, California
- Housing Market Analysis (Part I and II), 1945, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Memos, revised documents, "The Forum Study of the House Market"
- Federal Low Cost Housing and Minority Groups in San Francisco, 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Correspondence, Citizen Surveys of Public Housing, "Homemaking and Family Adjustment Services in Public Housing"
- Farm Housing -A case study, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- San Francisco Planning and Housing Association, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Correspondence, Memo, Minutes, News Article "Slum Clearance Plans in the Western Addition", "A Brief Legal Analysis of the Rise and Decline of the Restrictive Covenant Relating to Real Property Discriminating Against Persons on Account of Race and Color", Ping Yuen
- Wartime Housing-Japanese Section, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Correspondence, Reports, Recommendations, San Francisco Planning and Housing Association, National Housing Agency, Federal Public Housing Authority, "Japtown"
- Plans; "Housing Problem"; "1947 Bay Area Housing Survey"; "Survey of Housing Conditions in San Francisco", 1946-1947, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "Public Attitude Towards Housing in San Francisco with Particular Emphasis on the Activities of the San Francisco Housing Association", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence Regarding the Reconstruction and Development of the Bay Area Post WWII, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  "California Construction Rises to New High" (Report on Construction Contracts); "The People Design the City" Pamphlet
- Regulations Applicable to the Operation of the Allocations and Export Priorities System, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Department of Commerce: Office of Materials Distribution
- Veterans Emergency Housing Program; President Truman's Statement of December 14, 1946, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Correspondence, News Articles, Bulletins, Statements and plans regarding The Veterans Emergency Housing Program.
- News Clippings and Reports Relating to Unfair Treatment of Minorities in Housing, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  "Progress Against Prejudice"; "Open Occupancy in Public Housing"; Selected References on Housing of Minorities"; "Non-Discrimination Clauses in Regard to Public Housing and Urban Redevelopment Undertakings"
- Co-Op Housing in Chicago and Sweden, 1946, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- "Housing as an Outlet for Private Capital" and "Effect of the Corporate Income Tax on Investment in Rental Housing", 1940, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, Documentation, Guide, Legislation and News of Federal Rent Control (Act), 1947-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence and Booklets Relating to Minimum Requirements for Building Rental Housing Projects, 1938, 1942-1943, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  "Minimum Requirements for Rental Housing Projects", "Minimum Construction Requirements for New Dwellings Located in the Northern California District", "Your Building Code", Federal Housing Administration
- Correspondence, Guide and News Clippings Relating to (Updating) Building Codes in California, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Plans, Releases and Statements Related to Community Development in Yardville, Philadelphia, 1949; undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  "Yardville, USA Action Program", "The Philadelphia Story", "How not to Build Cities", "Yardville, USA Supplementary Program: McCall's Guide to Creating a Yardville in Your own Community"
- "Neighborhood Design and Control"; "A Checklist for the Review of Local Subdivision Controls", 1944, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Correspondence and Purchases Related to the Street Tree Program in California, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Financial Transactions Between Howard G. Hanvey Advertising Firm and Citizens Committee for Sewer Bonds, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  The San Francisco Bank. Special Savings Account Booklet
- Correspondence, Donations and (Master) Planning for "Sewers Come First" Campaign, 1944, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Firehouses in San Francisco, 1940, 1950, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Firehouse Bond, Firehouse tours and plans for Firehouses.
- Citizens' Postwar Planning Committee's Priorities and Correspondence, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Public Works, Airlines, Construction, etc.
- Bay Area Regional Planning, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Senate Bill, Minutes, Correspondence, etc.
- Donation to SPUR, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  San Francisco Planning and Urban Renewal Association
- Attitudes, Proposals Reports and Studies Regarding the Redevelopment of San Francisco, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Draft of "Group Attitudes and Urban Redevelopment"; "Community Revelopment Act of California"; "Memorandum for Redevelopment Committee"
- Resources for Buying and Building Houses, 1940-1945, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  "The Local Housing Authority and the Architect" and "Construction, Pacemaker of Progress"
- National Public Housing Conference, Inc, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Architect's Committee, National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, Inc., 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  "Britain Faces its Housing Emergency"; "American-Soviet Building Conference"; "Soviet Cities Rebuild"; "International Labor Review"
- Pan American Housing and Planning (Multiple Languages), 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  "Provisional Directory of Housing and Planing Agencies"; "Bulletin de Documentation"
- Nob Hill Rezoning, 1950, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "Zoning and Civic Development"; "American Society of Planning Officials" Newsletter, 1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  To promote efficiency of public administration in land and community planning
- "Outline of a Street Tree Program" and Correspondence, 1945, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  "Street Trees for Citie"
- Correspondence, Information, Report and Questionnaires Relating to "Presido Idle Acres" Campaign, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Quarrying Regulation Ordinance and "An Interior Greenbelt for San Francisco", 1939, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Correspondence, Requests, Ordinances, News Releases, Agendas and More.
- Correspondence and Proposed Amendments to Building Code Relating to Quarrying, Excavation and Grading, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence and News Clippings Relating to Dumping in the Alemany-Junipero Serra Boulevard Area/ Stanley Drive, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Municipal Railway Bond Issue, Rapid Traffic and Transportation Planning in San Francisco, 1939, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Documents Relating to Proposed 1953 Municipal Railway Reconstruction and Replacement Bond Issue, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Cable Cars, Rapid Traffic, Downtown San Francisco Parking and "A Study of the Effect of Land Acquisition for the Bayshore Freeway on San Francisco Industry", 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Citizens Committee to Save Cable Cars, Subcommittee Reports, Correspondence, Media Correction,
- Proposed Mayor's Program, "Master Plan of San Francisco: Studies for the Location of a Central Airline Bus Terminal"; Transit Modernization and Related Traffic Control Measures" and Proposed Mayors Program, 1946, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Mass Transit, Urban Transportation, Parking and Highways., 1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Proposals and Plans for Rapid Transit in San Francisco, 1931, 1936, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- San Francisco Transportation Committee Minutes, Proposals and Correspondence, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Documents Relating to Bay Area Rapid Transit Commission and Bill, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Bills and Documents Relating to Bay Crossings/Bridges, 1949-1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Key Systems Transit Lines, 1952-1956 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Plans and Reports for Local California Transportation Systems, 1947, 1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Hall of Flowers Exhibit Building in Golden Gate Park, 1949, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Aquatic Park Preservation Interior Greenbelt, Surface Freeways in Golden Gate Park Controversy and Small Boat Harbor, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Correspondence Relating to Various Properties Under San Francisco's Parks, Playground and Public Buildings Committee, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Angel Island, Aquatic Park, John McLaren Park, Palace of Fine Arts and Steam Boat Fort Sutter, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Correspondence and Notes Relating to Automobile Races, Civic Center, de Young Museum Public Library, Map of Proposed Extension of Palo Alto Avenue and the Preservation of Golden Gate Park, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Correspondence and Minutes Relating to Road Races in Golden Gate Park Proposal, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Relationship of Baltimore Plan to the Public Low-Rent Housing and Slum Clearance and Urban Redevelopment Programs; Community Night at Girls High School, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- "The Mayor of Baltimore Reports for 1948-1949" and Documents Relating to the Story of Yardsville, USA, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Correspondence, Documents and News Clippings Relating to Playspace Planning in Baltimore, 1950, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Planning Material for Open Space Development and the Baltimore Plan, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Materials and Documents Relating to San Francisco's Chinatown Recreational Plans and Housing Projects, 1950, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Booklets and Reports Relating to Recreational Facilities in American Cities, 1936, 1939-1941, 1946, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- "John McLaren Park Area Proposed General Plan" and Documents in Opposition, 1950, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Correspondence, News Clippings, and Documents Relating to the Butano Forest Bond Issue, 1948, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  Includes School Bond Issue
- Correspondence, Documents and News Clippings Relating to Land Uses For Angel Island, 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- San Francisco Recreation Department, 1940-1951 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Correspondence, Documents and Maps Relating to the Preservation of The Sunset Community Center, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  "The Sunset Community Center: An Achievement in Cooperative Planning 1946-1947"
- Correspondence and Articles Relating to Nursery Schools in the Bay Area, 1940, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- 1929 Map Marked With San Francisco's Hills and Relating Documents, 1929, 1944, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  Normal School
- City Planning in Public Elementary Schools, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- "City Planning as Studied in San Francisco Public Schools", Teaching Material and Correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Materials for City Planning in San Francisco's Public Schools and "San Francisco Social Studies Series", 1946, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Teacher's Materials. Six Booklets in the "San Francisco Social Studies Series"
- "Better Housing for the Family"; Housing for Family Living" and Planning Booklets Relating to Family Living., 1945, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Reports, Maps and Information Relating to Public Health and Civic Unity in San Francisco, 1938, 1940, 1945, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Adult Probation in San Francisco and "The Cost of Slums in Newark"; Surveys Included, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- The Price of Slums in San Francisco; "Blight and Taxes", 1947 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Documents, Photographs and Maps Relating to "Blight and Taxes" of San Francisco, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence and Articles Relating to "Blight and Taxes"; "Your Dollars ---Your Slums", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Youth Welfare and Juvenile Delinquency of California, 1941, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- "Report on Housing and Juvenile Delinquency"; Probation Office of Los Angeles' Monthly Reports"; "These Came Back" and News Clippings Relating to Juvenile Delinquency, 1937-1939, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Reports Relating to the Connection of Health, Housing and Sanitation in U.S. Cities., 1936-1937, 1941, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, Surveys and Documents Relating to the Housing Needs of Black, Chinese and Japanese Communities, 1930, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, Survey, Documents and Reports Relating to African Americans Living and Working in San Francisco, 1941-1944 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Documents and Promotional Material Relating to the Fight to Secure Property Rights for Minorities and Women, 1946-1950 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- "First Report of the San Francisco Housing Association", 1911 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Correspondence Relating to Proposal to Conduct Survey of Slum Area, 1933-1938 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- No Folder 16 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- "Now is the Time to Plan", San Francisco's Comprehensive Plan; Slum Clearance and Urban Redevelopment, 1943-1944, 1947-1952 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- San Francisco Planning and Housing Association's Role in Urban Redevelopment, 1944, 1947, 1952, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
- San Francisco Planning and Housing Association's Board of Directors Meetings and Planning Suggestions, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- San Francisco Planning and Housing Association Board of Directors Membership Invitations, Minutes and Responsibilities, 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- San Francisco Planning and Housing Association Board of Directors Business, 1950-1952 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, Amendments, Minutes and Support of San Francisco Planning and Housing Association Relating to Southern Crossing, 1953-1956 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- San Francisco Planning and Housing Association Board of Directors Executive Committee Meetings, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- San Francisco Planning and Housing Association Board of Directors Executive Committee Meetings II, 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- San Francisco Planning and Housing Association Board of Directors Executive Committee Meetings; Data and Dues of Members, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- San Francisco Planning and Housing Association Application for a Rosenberg Foundation Grant, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Correspondence and Reports Between the San Francisco Planning and Housing Association and the Rosenberg Foundation Relating to Grant, 1941-1942, 1944-1946 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Correspondence and Information Relating to the Columbia Foundation Grant, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Financial Information Relating to San Francisco Planning and Housing Association, 1940, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Financial Information Relating to San Francisco Planning and Housing Association II, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Financial Information Relating to San Francisco Planning and Housing Association III, 1950-1955 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Expenses, 1945-1953 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- "Record of Cash Received", 1944-1954 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- "Records of Checks Drawn", 1944-1954 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- "Record of Cash Received", "Distribution of Checks Drawn", "General Ledger", "Record of Journal Entries", and Expenses, 1944-1957 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Glass Slides (Box 4)